{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The first geostationary satellite launched in 1965 was called", "opta": "ANIK", "optb": "EARLY BIRD (Intelsat-I)", "optc": "WESTAR", "optd": "MOLNIYA", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rotation of a geosynchronous satellite means its", "opta": "drift from stationary position", "optb": "wobbling", "optc": "three-axis stabilization", "optd": "three-dimensional stabilization", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The present total cost per watt of power generation in geosynchronous orbit is nearly Rs.", "opta": "20", "optb": "50", "optc": "100", "optd": "5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Noise temperature of Sun is more than __________ \u00b0K.", "opta": "1000", "optb": "5000", "optc": "100000", "optd": "500", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A 20 m antenna gives a certain uplink gain at frequencies of 4/6 GHz. For getting same gain in the 20/30 GHz band, antenna size required is metre.", "opta": "100", "optb": "4", "optc": "1", "optd": "10", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discussing sharing of a communication satellite by many geographically dispersed Earth station, DAMA means", "opta": "Demand-Assigned Multiple Access", "optb": "Decibel Attenuated Microwave Access", "optc": "Digital Analog Master Antenna", "optd": "Dynamically-Assigned Multiple Access", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The angle subtended by earth at geostationary communication satellite is", "opta": "17.34\u00b0", "optb": "51.4\u00b0", "optc": "120\u00b0", "optd": "60\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The INTELSAT-IV satellite launched in 1974 had two earth coverage antenna and two narrower-angle antennas subtending 4.5\u00b0. The signal from narrow-angle antenna was stronger than that from earth- coverage antenna by a factor of", "opta": "17.34/4.5", "optb": "17.34 x 4.5", "optc": "(17.34/4.5)2", "optd": "(17.34/4.5)4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A transponder is a satellite equipment which", "opta": "receives a signal from Earth station and amplifies", "optb": "changes the frequency of the received signal", "optc": "retransmits the received signal", "optd": "does all of the above-mentioned functions", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A geosynchronous satellite", "opta": "has the same period a that of the Earth", "optb": "has a circular orbit", "optc": "rotates in the equatorial plane", "optd": "has all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "To make antenna more directional, either its size must be increased or", "opta": "the number of its feed horns must be increased", "optb": "the frequency of its transmission must be increased", "optc": "its effective isotropic radiated power (EIRP) must be increased", "optd": "its footprint must be increased", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "India's first domestic geostationary satellite 1NSAT-IA was launched on 10th April 1982 from", "opta": "USSR", "optb": "USA", "optc": "UK", "optd": "UP", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Satellite launch sites are invariably located on Eastern seaboards to ensure that", "opta": "launch takes place eastward", "optb": "expenditure of propulsion fuel is reduced during plane changing", "optc": "the satellite achieves circular orbit quickly", "optd": "spent rocket motor and other launcher debris falls into the sea", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The owner of a communication satellite is usually required to keep the spacecraft on station at its assigned place in the geosynchronous orbit with an accuracy of __________ degree.", "opta": "0.1", "optb": "1.0", "optc": "2.0", "optd": "0.5", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The number of days when Earth's shadow falls on a geosynchronous satellite is", "opta": "88", "optb": "277", "optc": "5", "optd": "10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Of the four INSAT-I satellites planned by India so for, only __________ has proved to be successful.", "opta": "INSAT-IA", "optb": "INSAT-IB", "optc": "INSAT-IC", "optd": "INSAT-ID", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Radio broadcasting is a familiar example of", "opta": "space multiplexing", "optb": "time multiplexing", "optc": "frequency multiplexing", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "As compared to 17.34\u00b0 antenna, the total increase in the signal relayed by 4.5\u00b0 antenna of INTELSAT-IV is", "opta": "14.85", "optb": "220", "optc": "78", "optd": "3.85", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements regarding DSI is wrong?", "opta": "It is a digital form of TASI", "optb": "Though it is more efficient than TASI, it is much slower", "optc": "A speaker has to wait (it at all) for only a few milliseconds for reallocation of channel", "optd": "It has increased the capacity of satellite channels by a factor of 2.2 or more with out degrading speech quality", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements regarding compandor is FALSE?", "opta": "It compresses the higher-amplitude parts of a signal before modulation and expands them back to normal again after demodulation.", "optb": "It gives preferential treatment to the weaker parts of the signal", "optc": "For weaker signals it gives a poor ratio of signal strength to quantizing error", "optd": "Weaker signals, traverse more quantum steps than they would do otherwise and so quantizing error is reduced.", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The quality of a space-link is measured in terms of the __________ ratio.", "opta": "C/N", "optb": "S/N", "optc": "G/T", "optd": "EIRP", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The useful operational life of INSAT-IB (launched in 1983) is expected to end by", "opta": "1992-93", "optb": "1991-92", "optc": "1989-90", "optd": "1993-94", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "At present, the radio-frequency band mainly used by most satellites is", "opta": "EHF", "optb": "UHF", "optc": "VHF", "optd": "SHF", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Orbital disturbances of a geosynchronous satellite are caused by the", "opta": "moon", "optb": "sun", "optc": "earth", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statement is correct?", "opta": "Satellite spacing is not affected by the bandwidth of the transmitting earth station", "optb": "Beamwidth is independent of antenna size and frequency band used", "optc": "The width of a beam in space is inversely proportional to the width of the transmitting antenna", "optd": "Use of high-frequency bands permits less number of satellites to share the orbit", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a stop-and-wait ARQ system, the transmitting terminal", "opta": "waits for positive or negative acknowled-gement from the receiving terminal after sending a block", "optb": "sends another block if positive acknowledge is received through ACK character", "optc": "resends the previous block if negative acknowledgement is received through a NAK character", "optd": "does not wait for acknowledgement after sending a block", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A geostationary satellite is one which", "opta": "hangs motionless in space about 36000 km about Earth", "optb": "travels around the Earth in 24 hours", "optc": "remains stationary above the Earth", "optd": "appears stationary to everybody on Earth", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The geostationary communication satellite APPLE is parked in the equatorial orbit at", "opta": "102\u00b0 E longitude over Sumatra", "optb": "90\u00b0 E longitude over Bangladesh", "optc": "74\u00b0 E longitude over India", "optd": "67\u00b0 E longitude over Pakistan", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Power received from Sun per m2 surface area of a geosynchronous satellite in nearly __________ watt.", "opta": "100", "optb": "500", "optc": "2000", "optd": "1000", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A certain sound has 10000 times more energy than another sound. The number of times it would sound stronger to a listener is", "opta": "40", "optb": "10000", "optc": "100", "optd": "10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "While keeping the down-link frequency constant, the diameter of a satellite antenna is reduced by half. To offer the same EIRP over the increased coverage area, the RF output power has to be increases by a factor of", "opta": "2", "optb": "4", "optc": "8", "optd": "16", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A communication satellite is a repeater between", "opta": "a transmitting station and a receiving station", "optb": "a transmitting station and many receiving station", "optc": "many transmitting station and many receiving station", "optd": "none", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ending part of the popular teleserial Mahabharat will be beamed to the viewers", "opta": "WESTAT", "optb": "INSAT-IC", "optc": "ARABSAT", "optd": "INSAT-ID", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most effective anti jamming technique is", "opta": "frequency hopping", "optb": "spread-spectrum modulation", "optc": "key leverage", "optd": "once-only key", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For satellite communication, standard Earth stations have antenna diameters in the range of __________ metre.", "opta": "27.5 to 30", "optb": "10 to 15", "optc": "30 to 50", "optd": "5 to 10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The Sun blots out the transmission of a geosynchronous satellite twice a year when satellite passes directly in front of it. This outage lasts for about", "opta": "10 minutes on 5 consecutive days", "optb": "5 minutes on 10 consecutive days", "optc": "30 minutes for 5 consecutive days", "optd": "one hour for 5 consecutive days", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In satellite communication, frequency modulation is used because satellite channel has", "opta": "small bandwidth and negligible noise", "optb": "large bandwidth and severe noise", "optc": "maximum bandwidth and minimum noise", "optd": "high modulation index", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the case of a 70-MHz IF carrier for a transponder bandwidth of 36 MHz, energy must lie between MHz.", "opta": "34 and 106", "optb": "52 and 88", "optc": "106 and 142", "optd": "34 and 142", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following factor does NOT contribute to the drift of a geostationary satellite from its stationary position in space?", "opta": "Pressure of solar radiations", "optb": "Gravitational changes due to Sun and Moon", "optc": "Oblateness of the Earth", "optd": "Weight of the satellite", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In communication satellites, the up-link normally operates at a higher frequency than the down-link because it", "opta": "gives a narrow beam shining into space", "optb": "results in lesser signal attenuation", "optc": "gives better beam-shaping", "optd": "is easier to polarize a high frequency beam", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For global communication, the number of satellites needed is", "opta": "1", "optb": "3", "optc": "10", "optd": "5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}